Shavelson, Clara Lemlich Photographs 6131 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Clara Lemlich Shavelson Photographs
1957-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Shavelson, Clara Lemlich
6131 P
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Photographs.
7992946
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 13, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, August 19, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Clara Lemlich Shavelson (1886-1982) forced union leaders to acknowledge the importance of female workers in the labor force, and she organized important demonstrations for worker's rights and cost-of-living issues.
Shavelson worked for the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union organizing women in 1905, arguing that without women workers, any strike was doomed to failure. She forced her way into speaking at the 1909 strike meeting at Cooper Union. Her fiery speech set off the 'Uprising of the 20,000', the largest strike by women workers to that time.
Shavelson was blacklisted from factory work for a time. But, returned in 1917 to fight cost-of-living issues during the kosher meat boycott. And again in 1919 during the rent strike movement when a housing shortage raised rents. By 1929 she was helping found what became the Progressive Women's Council, which combat depredations of the Great Depression by running a meat boycott that shut down 4,500 butcher shops in New York.
Shavelson continued her activism intor her final years, organizing the orderlies at her nursing home.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6131: Clara Lemlich Shavelson Miscellany 6131 AV: Clara Lemlich Shavelson Audio-Visual Materials
Shavelson, Clara Lemlich, 1886-1982; Margules, Rita
7992946
- Clara Shavelson with younger woman and 3 children under cherry trees, ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  "B174" on back
- Informal group photo of three elder women including Clara Shavelson and a young girl, all in informal clothing, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  "New York, August 1957" on back
- Woman sitting outdoors with young girl on her lap - possibly Rita and her daughter (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Circa 1940s?
- Informal outdoor portrait of an elder woman, perhaps carrying a camera case or purse, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clara Shavelson and Rita Margules, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  "To Mom with Love, Rita, taken June 1973" on back
- Clara Shavelson and Rita Margules, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Informal photo of an outdoor meal with men and woman gathered around a table (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Circa 1960s
- Two men and a woman pose next to a brick wall (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Portrait of a young girl (Box 1, Folder 9)
  "I give my card as a keepsake to Aunt Klara from Zoey" on back, in Russian
- Postcard studio portrait of a young man in uniform seated with another man standing behind him (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Negatives (Box 1, Folder 11)